Suraj Racha: module.
Sattvastha Ventures: Oh.
Suraj Racha: A very warm, good evening to all of us who are in Bharat.
Suraj Racha: And good morning and good afternoon, according to your own respective places.
Suraj Racha: We'll just take a quick 5 minutes to introduce to our instructors today, and just run through a few more important instructions, and then we'd like to welcome Goinjian to start with the programs.
Suraj Racha: Before that, myself, I'm Sury Turksha from IIT Bombay, and, part of Bidur.
Suraj Racha: With this?
Suraj Racha: I'd like to share something, very interesting.
Suraj Racha: So… First of all?
Suraj Racha: Welcome to, welcome to the Counselor Training Program.
Suraj Racha: And The speakers for today, actually not speakers, but…
GOVINDA Das: Can you speak louder?
GOVINDA Das: Let me speak more… more.
GOVINDA Das: Come closer to the mic.
Suraj Racha: Yeah.
Suraj Racha: Huh, it's… Is it better? Hello?
Suraj Racha: Is it better?
Sattvastha Ventures: Oh, yeah, you're a little better now.
Suraj Racha: So, the speakers for today, or rather the instructions for today.
Suraj Racha: instructors for today is, we are having Goin Dasji, who is a Vedic psychology guide and counseling expert. So, Goindji has been spearheading many, many guru books and alternative educational institutes throughout India. He's an author, he's a scholar in, scriptures like Ramayan, Mahavarath, and Bhagavad Gita.
Suraj Racha: He is an educationalist who has spent more than 30 decades in alternative and IKS-based education systems, and is also expert in IKS-based psychology, which we'll be seeing today. Along with Goenji, we are having Dr. Karin Mitchell.
Suraj Racha: Another very profound instructor, who is a psychology expert and counseling trainer.
Suraj Racha: The expertise of Karanji is he has done MBBS, in a physician by profession, he has also done MSc in Counseling, then MA in Philosophy, Nya in Jupesh, and now also pursuing his PhD in Indian Psychology. But the beauty is, more than… for more than 6 years.
Suraj Racha: Karenji has integrated various subjects together to give a very integrated counseling mechanism, so this has been his expertise.
Suraj Racha: We would like to welcome both Gwenji and Karindi.
Suraj Racha: whole painting program.
Suraj Racha: Now, we're also having some more important announcements. Number one, because you all have participated for the program, which I'm very grateful for,
Suraj Racha: We are having… we are actually giving a 6-month subscription for the Vidur application. We are having a Vidur application, which I'll just demonstrate in some time.
Suraj Racha: And all of us will be getting a 6-month complimentary subscription. The app is trained, it's having a trained chatbot, journaling, there's a parameter guidance, assessment, tracks planner, a content library.
Lavina: Okay.
Suraj Racha: Now…
Suraj Racha: What we can do with the application, another thing which may be useful, because many of us here in the audience are, they are, they are, in some sense, counselors, they may be spiritual experts, they may be psychologists, clinicians, or, maybe dealing with, spearheading many education institutes.
Suraj Racha: There's a very interesting opportunity on the weather application platform. You can onboard your own community. So basically, you can onboard your community
Suraj Racha: you will get, you will be able to use the various tools which are there on our platform, and have a constant, and have a constant connect with all your mentors and your clients. So basically, this allows you to make IKS as the base of whatever you're doing.
Suraj Racha: And then, your natural connection with your counselors is, with your mentees is maintained.
Suraj Racha: With this, I'd like to… Run you through our application.
Suraj Racha: Very briefly, to get a feel of…
Suraj Racha: To get a feel of what our application looks like, what it offers.
Suraj Racha: Number one, we are having…
Suraj Racha: We are having a dashboard where you can track their move energy levels, so there's more than 11 parameters, and it's a daily tracking which you can do. You or your clients can do.
Suraj Racha: People can… people can generally connect, then…
Suraj Racha: We are having a chatbot. So, this chatbot is totally trained on the Indian Knowledge System. We have, collected a huge plenty of data from psychology, from the Shastras, and from integrated practices. So, this chatbot, offers that platform.
Suraj Racha: Now…
Suraj Racha: Another thing which we'd like you to try when you get access to the application, by the way, this, these all features are also available on the website, so application, website, both can be accessed. We are
Suraj Racha: Good, huh?
Suraj Racha: Eastern website, whatever possible.
Suraj Racha: given a lot of assessments, which are based upon, Indian knowledge system, especially the Kitta Bhumi, when we are having toughitavaza, then nakshatra-based assessments, Satra Thomas-based assessments, which are designed by experts.
Suraj Racha: So, once you answer them…
Suraj Racha: You get your own reports generated, you can get your counselor reports also on the platforms.
Suraj Racha: So, just as an example.
Suraj Racha: Just as an example, we like to view my report here.
Suraj Racha: And… Once this session gets over, you'll… you please take a hand over the application.
Suraj Racha: or presenting the post, it will be very useful.
Sattvastha Ventures: distinct.
Sattvastha Ventures: So, Raj, you're sounding quite distanced. Can you be either a little louder or come closer to your mic, please?
Suraj Racha: I bet.
Suraj Racha: I haven't heard.
Sattvastha Ventures: No, it's not audible.
Sattvastha Ventures: It's breaking, your voice seems to be breaking.
jithendra myla: It was better earlier.
jithendra myla: Now it was breaking.
GOVINDA Das: And… Karen, you can start…
GOVINDA Das: And then eventually, Suraj can fix up his things, and he can do the presentation later.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, sir.
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. Namaste, everyone, and…
Suraj Racha: Am I auditing mute now?
GOVINDA Das: Suraj, you stop now, we will do later.
Suraj Racha: Absolutely.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, it's not, not very clear, because the…
GOVINDA Das: The app presentation has to be clear, because there is a vibration of your voice.
GOVINDA Das: So let Karan begin, and in the conclude, then you can give.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, namaste, everyone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… Thank you, Prabhuji, for allowing me to… allowing me to co-train this workshop along with you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oh.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. Yes. So… To begin with.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, our Parampara basically starts with asking the right questions, and that's how Arishis have built their internal knowledge systems. So, to begin with this whole, whole training, which is the Level 1 training, I would like you to contemplate on one question to begin with.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And what's mind?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And you don't need to kind of qualify that definition with any of your understandings, but whatever first word comes to your mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: When I ask you the question, what is the mind? Just, just contemplate on that word, just let it kind of sink.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And see which word comes up.
Dr. Karan Mittal: People have hundreds of different words that can come up with that single definition, and I'll just allow you a minute to write your definition down.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so we don't need to, you know, explain the definition. I just wanted you to stay with this question.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And for the next 2 hours, or maybe even this whole module, I want you to understand how the definition of mind that our rishis have given us, and what we are currently holding, how it evolves for you, how it changes for you. So, people might have written different words, probably tomorrow in the group, I would ask you to share your words, so that we see what are the common words that evolve.
Dr. Karan Mittal: All the participants. But that's how we begin about the contemplation, that what is mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Mana, kaho.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And…
Dr. Karan Mittal: If we go to see the Indian knowledge systems, like, like, there are four pertinent questions that our Rishis have answered, and that's how the Indian knowledge systems have evolved. Out of the four pertinent questions, I've taken the… I've taken two questions. Who am I?
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's your question. And of course, these answers… answers to these questions can come from scriptures, from your trainings, from… from educational background that you hold, from your experience. So that's one question. There's the other question that what is world, and how do I see the world?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so basically, if I had to put it in Arishi's terminally, what is Jeeva? Who am I, and what is Jagat? What's the word?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the answers that you get to this question will actually define of how we view psychology from the Indic perspective.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If I have an individualistic perspective towards myself, that I am a being separate from others, distinct from others, myness is very strong, or my Hankar is very strong, then I'll view the psychology in a very individualistic
Dr. Karan Mittal: But when I look at the world as being a family, Vasudeva Kutumbakam, or any other of these indigenous words, or worldviews that we have, then our psychology is also driven by the social environment that we are staying in, the country we are staying in, the dharma we belong to.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, depending upon how you define the existence of yourself, as well as the world, is how you kind of train the psychology.
Dr. Karan Mittal: what we see in the Western view is that psychology became very individualistic. We kind of started focusing more on ourselves, and even in the individualistic
Dr. Karan Mittal: perspective, we separated the being into components. So when we look at one particular component, our definition, our interventions, our understanding of diseases, our understanding of behavior, is only kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: it is only, you know, circulating around that particular definition. But when I kind of start expanding the definition of I, from myself, to probably family, to social, environment, to country, to the world, that's how the perspective towards mind also changes. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so you could think of yourself as just the body, you could think of yourself as a Jeeva, as Atma, as an eternal being. These are the trainings that we get from our… from our Indian modules. So that's one perspective of looking at yourself. And then, how do we see the world? Do we see the world as mechanistic, operating on the laws of physics?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Do we see the world as being interconnected with each other? The countries, the people, the planets, the stars being interconnected? Do we see the world as a sacred thing, like it's the creation of the god, or creation of a higher being? Or do we see it as a random Big Bang Theory example?
Dr. Karan Mittal: on these things, if you see… if you see across the indigenous cultures, like, not just India, but all the indigenous cultures that existed in the world, this
Dr. Karan Mittal: world consciousness was, you know, kind of stood out separately in all the indigenous cultures, that we had Gaia consciousness, we had Mother Earth consciousness, we have, we have our own therapy and Umi in India. So these consciousnesses kind of… kind of built a fabric that kind of few…
Dr. Karan Mittal: All the people together, and that's how our psychologies became more interconnected.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And when the psychologies are interconnected, my pain doesn't just remain my pain, it becomes the world's pain, and my happiness just remains my happiness, it becomes world's happiness. So that's how it kind of buffers,
Dr. Karan Mittal: the intensity of everything. It doesn't allow you to get into deepest of your depressions, nor does it kind of take you to the other extreme.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so I want you to kind of dwell on these two questions, and probably
Dr. Karan Mittal: Over the period of time, again, probably tomorrow, we'll also discuss these questions in detail, that how do you see yourself
Dr. Karan Mittal: from a scriptural painting, it could just be an Atma or a jiva, etc. But maybe 5 to 7 words as you go deeper in the layers, like, I see myself as a body, I see myself as a sun, etc. These words will give you an understanding, and in the hierarchy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: As the hierarchy goes down, you'll see how much of what affects me. So if I see myself strongly as the son of my parents, any problem of my parents will start affecting me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If I see myself strongly billing, you know, belonging to a company or an institution as a CEO, as a director, their problems become mine.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so the hierarchy that kind of runs in your subconscious about your self-concept will determine what affects you in what intensity, and vice versa. The more generalized is your worldview, the more broader is your worldview.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Similarly, the deep… the lesser of your problems become your problems, it becomes more like a general… generalized spread that spreads across the world.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: So, thank you for joining with us.
GOVINDA Das: So, the three pillars of psychologist. Since we are… Hoping…
GOVINDA Das: That everyone was there in this group.
GOVINDA Das: Is some kind of counselor.
GOVINDA Das: Either spiritual counselor or professional counselor.
GOVINDA Das: But what do we lack is the Indian knowledge system.
GOVINDA Das: When we are spiritual counselors, Generally, our…
GOVINDA Das: Focus. Our reference point, is pure spiritual for everything.
GOVINDA Das: Consciously or unconsciously.
GOVINDA Das: Or, if you're a pure professional counselor having your degree.
GOVINDA Das: Especially in Baharat, if you study the history of psychology.
GOVINDA Das: It is governed and controlled by… the left liberal
GOVINDA Das: Abrahamic idea in the psychology study.
GOVINDA Das: Even though, in their home, they may be practicing some spirituality, some religiosity.
GOVINDA Das: But when it comes to giving knowledge.
GOVINDA Das: They do not have the resources to integrate between their education And their tradition.
GOVINDA Das: I remember talking to… the last Marastra Chief Minister's Officer on special duty.
GOVINDA Das: Because he and his wife run, Something related to psychology.
GOVINDA Das: For the orphans, also.
GOVINDA Das: And he was explaining very interesting point, that how
GOVINDA Das: That simply by the modern psychology, consciously or unconsciously.
GOVINDA Das: We break the roots of the client.
GOVINDA Das: They may not know how they're breaking it.
GOVINDA Das: But that is how it is designed.
GOVINDA Das: And we'll discuss about this. There is a cognitive bias.
GOVINDA Das: We will… we will try to discuss that today.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, what does Bharati Yata, since it is Indian knowledge system.
GOVINDA Das: What does Bharati Yata do? Bharati Yata…
GOVINDA Das: Bharatiyata gives the mind of the Bharat.
GOVINDA Das: And that mind of the Bharat In Roots, it is integrated.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Is it universal in its approach.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, the three pillars of psychologists, first is the disposition.
GOVINDA Das: Right, gives empathy to what you do.
GOVINDA Das: Alright? There is an empathy, disposition. The psychologist, psychologist, psychologist's disposition, and the disposition of the client.
GOVINDA Das: I remember I was talking to somebody.
GOVINDA Das: That imagine you are a lady psychologist.
GOVINDA Das: And you receive a client where both husband and wife
GOVINDA Das: They have an issue where the husband is an abuser.
GOVINDA Das: It is but natural, rather than seeing the client as a diseased person.
GOVINDA Das: We will see him as a criminal.
GOVINDA Das: If you're a police officer, it is your responsibility to file a case against him.
GOVINDA Das: But now he has come as a client.
GOVINDA Das: Right? So, such a disposition of seeing him as a criminal
GOVINDA Das: Does not help him to heal.
GOVINDA Das: Because now we are judging it.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, disposition is extremely important.
GOVINDA Das: Alright? Disposition is like having the…
GOVINDA Das: Udha Sinatha. Udha Sinatha is not indifferent.
GOVINDA Das: Udha sinatha means not having an attachment.
GOVINDA Das: with our client.
GOVINDA Das: Second.
GOVINDA Das: Once we have the right disposition, it gives rise to right understanding, because there are no layers. It is a pure filter.
GOVINDA Das: No, we understand them properly, we understand ourselves properly.
GOVINDA Das: So the disposition gives rise to right understanding.
GOVINDA Das: And the third, is the skill.
GOVINDA Das: Which gives rise to right communication, right outreach, and proper impact.
GOVINDA Das: In the Mahabharat, the great Vidura.
GOVINDA Das: he explained to Dhritarashtra four pillars of success in regards to anything.
GOVINDA Das: Including being the counselor. What are the four things he said?
GOVINDA Das: First is… Yoga.
GOVINDA Das: Yoga means what? Yoga means? Knowing very well what are my resources.
GOVINDA Das: All that resource has to be collected properly.
GOVINDA Das: Maya Bhutti… My knowledge, my information, my resources.
GOVINDA Das: And what I see, what we see, both the spiritual counselors And the professional counselors.
GOVINDA Das: In regards to Bharatiya Manasa Shastra, there is a great poverty.
GOVINDA Das: And the purpose of this seminar and the app itself, Suraj would explain to you how this app will become a better tool for you to do what you're already doing.
GOVINDA Das: So, what he says, yoga. Yoga means resources are very important.
GOVINDA Das: Second, raga. Raga means… Having the right mentor, even for the counselors.
GOVINDA Das: Humanities, if you see, again, as I said, all humanities subjects
GOVINDA Das: they screw up Indian tradition completely.
GOVINDA Das: They have built up such a narrative.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: They do not empower in the name of freeing you from the guilt. One of the main core principles of modern psychology is to make you free from guilt.
GOVINDA Das: Very important.
GOVINDA Das: But along with making you free from guilt, they also consciously, unconsciously make one shameless.
GOVINDA Das: Guilt-free is not equivalent to being free from responsibility.
GOVINDA Das: Responsibility is not a burden.
GOVINDA Das: Responsibility gives rise to empowerment.
GOVINDA Das: Right? So therefore, yoga, raga, right, knowledge system.
GOVINDA Das: changes complete narrative, just like this new movie called as Durandar.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: It is based upon very deep philosophy, because the person who directed, he comes from a background of Kashmiri Shaivaism.
GOVINDA Das: I was talking to some students from Delhi, They're from typical liberal college, And just by watching one
GOVINDA Das: movie, there is so much of change. Imagine the power of narratives.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, so therefore, yoga raga.
GOVINDA Das: And the third principle is… Dakshata. Dakshata means skill, right?
GOVINDA Das: The skill To interact with ourselves and with our clients.
GOVINDA Das: And the fourth is…
GOVINDA Das: The, the strategy, right time, what to speak, when to speak, what not to speak.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, this workshop is equal to understanding, without the soil.
GOVINDA Das: No roots. Without the roots, no fruit.
GOVINDA Das: The foundational idea becomes the important principle. With that, whatever you have learned simply becomes very powerful medium to… for…
GOVINDA Das: Becoming a impactful counselor.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'll just add one point.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How understanding, kind of, helps in clinical practice.
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, we as Indians have grown with the concepts of karma, with the concepts of God, with the concepts of salsparas, all these concepts we have heard right from our childhood, and somewhere or the other, they have created an impression in our minds. Now, an Indian psychologist or psychotherapist, without
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, if he doesn't use this background in his clinical practice, it's his foolishness. Because when you're talking to a client, and the client is strongly into karma, is strongly into these areas, using these techniques can sometimes help the therapist in giving results better, or faster.
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, in, like, in COVID, I remember, because there was a, like, increase in the number of clients having, you know, symptoms of anxiety and all that stuff during COVID, but… but…
Dr. Karan Mittal: just believing in the law of karma, believing in the law of, like, Ishvara, etc, kind of helped them, as India also as a whole, kind of helped them alleviate their symptoms in a much better, faster, and a healthier way.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so the… it's… it's like Jung also, Carl Jung also sometimes have… has used these philosophies, that whatever are the indigenous concepts, it's always useful to use these indigenous concepts in your counseling, in your sessions, because these… this has, you know, shaped the fabric of our life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It was…
GOVINDA Das: So… Again, when we study the psychology, Right?
GOVINDA Das: In regards to studying medicine, there is a hierarchy. Dr. Karan is a…
GOVINDA Das: student. He has done his MBBS from, Nair Medical College in Mumbai.
GOVINDA Das: there is an authority, there is a system, right? There is a hierarchy in regards to modern medicine.
GOVINDA Das: But when it comes to psychology.
GOVINDA Das: Yesterday, I remember talking to one student, Asking what is mind?
GOVINDA Das: We'll come to that.
GOVINDA Das: It is very difficult to define what is mine.
GOVINDA Das: We explain the… Functions of the mind, but we do not Define the mind.
GOVINDA Das: Think about it.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, even the experts of the modern psychologists say, they say.
GOVINDA Das: Psychology is not a history, it is a set of histories.
GOVINDA Das: there are a lot of integrated, conflicting opinion amongst the riches of the modern psychologists from the Western world.
GOVINDA Das: Bingley from Socrates to Carl Jung and Freud also.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, so, we will touch it very, very…
GOVINDA Das: In essence, because you have studied, those who have studied it, they have studied it.
GOVINDA Das: Those who have not studied, they will have some glimpse of it, because the purpose is not to introduce you to the modern psychology.
GOVINDA Das: For that, you may take a separate degree. Ours is focused on Indian knowledge system.
GOVINDA Das: Now, Socrates… His idea of psychology because even the Prabhupahad.
GOVINDA Das: He explained that Socrates knew Brahman.
GOVINDA Das: thinkers like Socrates said psychology begins with knowing yourself, your thoughts and actions.
GOVINDA Das: You can see here, for Socrates, mind is as good as the Atma.
GOVINDA Das: And then he adds, Thoughts and actions.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: And they build up a lot of knowledge based upon that.
GOVINDA Das: And his student, Plato, He went little further. He said, mind as a structure.
GOVINDA Das: Plato explains that minus parts, reason, emotion, and desire.
GOVINDA Das: That must be balanced. Again, it's talking about the function.
GOVINDA Das: Right? It has a reason, it has emotion, it has desire. Now, reason, if you see carefully, reason is not part of the mind.
GOVINDA Das: from the Bharati Adarshti Kon. It is part of the Buddhi.
GOVINDA Das: Desire and emotions are part of the mind.
GOVINDA Das: Third, Aristotle, the student of Plato.
GOVINDA Das: You know, he did a lot of study on, you know, biology also.
GOVINDA Das: Habits shape personality.
GOVINDA Das: Somewhere is touching about samskaras.
GOVINDA Das: Aristotle emphasized that repeated actions create character.
GOVINDA Das: We become what we do.
GOVINDA Das: Somewhere is catching in the middle, is not going into the roots, as Dr. Karanje was speaking about, promoterie.
GOVINDA Das: Again, we speak about the grace of God.
GOVINDA Das: we speak about the sadhana.
GOVINDA Das: But when you talk about karma, karma is a very offensive subject, because it is presented like that.
GOVINDA Das: And for Indian psychology, the concept of karma is very important.
GOVINDA Das: For your information, even if you study Ayurved.
GOVINDA Das: In Ayurved, the colleges do not teach the theory of karma, because it is an offensive subject.
GOVINDA Das: Reincarnation is not taught in Ayurved.
GOVINDA Das: Because it has to be made secular. Because karma offends people.
GOVINDA Das: The word karma is not only connected to the past.
GOVINDA Das: The world karma is connected to empowerment.
GOVINDA Das: It's very important.
GOVINDA Das: and very interesting principles. So, therefore, Aristotle touched a little bit about karma which is happening now. He did not touch upon the karma which has happened in the past.
GOVINDA Das: He's not talking about the samskaras, he's talking about the condition, the modern conditioning.
GOVINDA Das: Simple. Like, if you're traveling in Mumbai.
GOVINDA Das: Your school teacher may say that one should stand in line.
GOVINDA Das: But when you come to the train station at the Borivilo or Church Gate, you don't stand in line, because the conditioning is to rush inside.
GOVINDA Das: So, conditioning is always more powerful than the information.
GOVINDA Das: But the same person, when he comes to metro station.
GOVINDA Das: Because the metro has a different conditioning, people will stand in line.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, what Aristotle is saying is real.
GOVINDA Das: If you create a conditioning, people change their habit.
GOVINDA Das: If you create conditioning and give proper information that conditioning is a knowledge.
GOVINDA Das: But conditioning is always greater than information.
GOVINDA Das: This is one, Karin?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Rojit?
GOVINDA Das: So therefore, therefore, before we continue to the next part of the Western psychology.
GOVINDA Das: This is a very interesting… I did this exercise to our school teacher in, Vrindara and Neville School.
GOVINDA Das: What you are now.
GOVINDA Das: What is your identity now?
GOVINDA Das: Next, what you want it to be. You please write it down.
GOVINDA Das: Now, what you are now, you can… you can use…
GOVINDA Das: the ink which was used by Hamza in the movie.
GOVINDA Das: Not known to others.
GOVINDA Das: Right? What you are now, so that you are honest to yourself.
GOVINDA Das: We are not asking the answer about this.
GOVINDA Das: Apke le hai, Pura.
GOVINDA Das: Right, what you are now… What do you want it to be?
GOVINDA Das: And how you landed where you are today.
GOVINDA Das: Is there is a gap between what you want it to be and what you are now?
GOVINDA Das: And do you actually know how you landed here?
GOVINDA Das: Or is it an accident?
GOVINDA Das: Or it is a passchata, but hey, why did I come into this area?
GOVINDA Das: Or you have the understanding, okay, I came because of this four reasons.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Because…
GOVINDA Das: The interesting part, if you study Bhagavad Gita, again, Bhagavad Gita is one of the most amazing psychology books.
GOVINDA Das: But some other, we only focus on the spiritual aspect of Bhagavad Gita.
GOVINDA Das: Which is very important, no doubt, because it is integrated.
GOVINDA Das: The spirituality is there.
GOVINDA Das: But, at the same time, Arjuna was not asking spiritual inquiry from Krishna.
GOVINDA Das: Arjun was asking Krishna about how do it… how did I land here?
GOVINDA Das: Right? On that spot, he was a warrior, but he wanted to be a beggar.
GOVINDA Das: So, please take 2-3 minutes.
GOVINDA Das: Write it down, please.
GOVINDA Das: on your phone, or at least on your notebook, we will give 2 minutes for this.
GOVINDA Das: And, we will see how we take it forward.
GOVINDA Das: If you're done with it, If you want to share, if anybody wants to share, one or two.
GOVINDA Das: Members, if they want to share.
GOVINDA Das: They can do it.
GOVINDA Das: If not, you can keep it with yourself.
GOVINDA Das: For reflecting and studying your own self.
GOVINDA Das: Or you're still figuring out.
Renuka Bhuta: That provocation.
GOVINDA Das: Yes. But you want to share, or you want to just keep it with yourself?
Renuka Bhuta: Yes, I can share, sir, Prabhuji.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, okay.
Renuka Bhuta: As of now, I've become a professional and a better person.
Renuka Bhuta: I wanted to be granny.
Renuka Bhuta: But, life lesson and finances, made me where I've landed up now.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Anybody else?
jithendra myla: Very traditional approaching. Yeah, I mean…
jithendra myla: I've been part of ISCON for a long time, for 15 years, but… So, the question on the mind always puzzles me. I used to ask several speakers on the mine.
jithendra myla: Where does the mind stay in the body? Like, I always thought it's in the brain somewhere.
jithendra myla: And then…
jithendra myla: The mind also, I feel like… I mean, this is my own conclusion, I feel like… I came to… no one given me proper answer, so I came to my own conclusion, where the mind is what… basically what we eat, what…
jithendra myla: The food that we eat, if it is
jithendra myla: impure food, not, like, materially impure, but, spiritually, I mean.
jithendra myla: food, like, people, when they cook, when they eat, when they watch TV, or they talk some politics or some other else.
jithendra myla: And then food becomes also pure, and then when we eat it, it becomes… Or blood.
jithendra myla: And the blood is basically our conscious, and then…
jithendra myla: That's how the mind becomes so agitated, and then it will force us to do things, which we don't want to do with conscious.
jithendra myla: And, yeah, the… That's, and for me, I'm not able to control mine, like.
jithendra myla: I'm able to control several things right now. My problems are whenever I do so productive work in the whole day, and then…
jithendra myla: I'm addicted to watching the phone, for messages, for watching the YouTube short videos, Facebook videos, for different kind of content, like, it can be politics or different things, like geopolitics.
jithendra myla: It's so addictive, and then that's affecting my, productivity every day.
jithendra myla: And also, yeah, and… Yeah, that's, where I am right now.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, anybody else? But specifically on this, what are you now? What do you want it to be, how you landed where you are today?
GOVINDA Das: Anybody else?
GOVINDA Das: Yes, yes, Vikram.
Vikram Chakilam: Oh… I'll answer the second and third… Who answered the… Last one.
GOVINDA Das: Not about the mind, we want to focus on this one.
Vikram Chakilam: Yes, yes.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, yeah.
Vikram Chakilam: I have answers for second and third questions.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
Vikram Chakilam: You please help me the answer for the first one.
Vikram Chakilam: Okay, what you wanted to be is, like, I wanted to be a wise counselor helping others grow.
Vikram Chakilam: Wholeheartedly, from my heart.
Vikram Chakilam: And how you landed where you are today?
Vikram Chakilam: I was, focusing on helping others, rather than empowering… empowering myself.
Vikram Chakilam: I'm not happy with that. I learned very, swimming lessons very… in a very hard way.
GOVINDA Das: Hmm.
Vikram Chakilam: So, what you are now? I don't know.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, good one, thank you. So, we'll proceed further. You can… it's very important. These reflections are very important, because
GOVINDA Das: You know, it will help our disposition, our understanding, and our skills.
GOVINDA Das: And then, when we talk to the clients, you know, the council is…
GOVINDA Das: those who we want to help also, then it becomes easier. See? You know, how he's an educated person, he's a spiritualist, he has raised family, he's a grandfather also, right? So, and he's honest to share that.
GOVINDA Das: So please write it down, we will… we will revisit that, so we'll continue with our next part, yeah.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: So, they… The next one, is the scritters, Thinking defines existence.
GOVINDA Das: Right? He talked about… You know, our thought process, our very thought becomes our identity.
GOVINDA Das: Like, if you study some of the great historians, Right?
GOVINDA Das: See, the unfortunate reality, whether all these philosophers
GOVINDA Das: They begin from their own surrounding.
GOVINDA Das: We will study again. Sometime the existent defines our thinking.
GOVINDA Das: Please focus on this.
GOVINDA Das: When you say thinking defines our existence, this is somewhere you start in the middle.
GOVINDA Das: In the beginning of the creation, we talk about the beginning of the creation, Srishti, Prakriti, Right?
GOVINDA Das: Actually, we will come to that. Our thinking is based upon the definition of our existence.
GOVINDA Das: Our existence defines our thinking. Our thinking does not define our existence to us.
GOVINDA Das: If you are existing in Mumbai, your thinking is different.
GOVINDA Das: Your habits are different.
GOVINDA Das: The same person, Mumbai person, when he goes to Singapore, he or she goes to Singapore, their thinking differs.
GOVINDA Das: A human being is extremely… Affected by his surrounding, and their thinking changes.
GOVINDA Das: Their thinking is not constant based upon the changing situation, changing existence.
GOVINDA Das: Rather, his thinking changes based upon where do they exist.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, so he focused on thinking defines our existence, because he was a philosopher. His ahar and Nidra Bhai Maitun was taken care.
GOVINDA Das: Hume, another great philosopher.
GOVINDA Das: Mind is ever-changing. David Hume believed the self is just flow of changing thoughts and feelings, much deeper in one sense.
GOVINDA Das: Right? He's able to grasp a little bit that self is just the flow of changing thoughts and feelings, like…
GOVINDA Das: Chandra, in the Jyotes Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: Again, this is another Vedic science, right? One of the greatest signs for studying the mind.
GOVINDA Das: Jyotes Shastra is one of the greatest signs to study the mind, buddy, and Ahankar. The core study of Jyoteshya depends on these three principles only, studying mind, studying ego, and studying our intelligence.
GOVINDA Das: Right? And the moon planet, which is connected to the mind, is most flickering.
GOVINDA Das: Every planet in a zodiac sign, they travel.
GOVINDA Das: The Saturn planet takes two and a half years from one zodiac sign to other zodiac sign.
GOVINDA Das: Saturn represents justice.
GOVINDA Das: Justice is… justice always takes time, even in the planetary position.
GOVINDA Das: But the feelings…
GOVINDA Das: The moon travels in one… from one zodiac sign to other zodiac sign within two and a half days.
GOVINDA Das: See the gap between the justice
GOVINDA Das: And the feeling. Feeling travels from one zodiac sign to other zodiac sign within two and a half days.
GOVINDA Das: Now, Parashar Maharshi wrote this, the father of Yasudev.
GOVINDA Das: How many of us, we have an issue with Jyotih Shastra?
GOVINDA Das: Some are slanderous about it.
GOVINDA Das: Some undermine it, Some say it is a science, but not applicable in this time and age.
GOVINDA Das: Right? While being practitioners of spirituality.
GOVINDA Das: We defy one of the core anger of the Vedas.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, so therefore, Hume caught little bit.
GOVINDA Das: Mind is ever-changing.
GOVINDA Das: An ever-changing mind gives a different definition.
GOVINDA Das: I was talking to someone.
GOVINDA Das: And very devout spiritualist.
GOVINDA Das: But now, on the verge of losing all the faith.
GOVINDA Das: And why losing the faith? Because…
GOVINDA Das: There is an issue of the surrounding.
GOVINDA Das: So, we will discuss that also. The faith was based upon the mind.
GOVINDA Das: And lack of faith was based upon the mind, and mind was based upon the surrounding.
GOVINDA Das: And the surrounding was favorable, the faith was intact. When the surrounding was not favorable, faith was shaken. Mind is shaken, existence is also shaken.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, Karan.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so when we began the session, there were 3 pertinent questions that we asked.
Dr. Karan Mittal: what's your self-concept, and what's… what's… what's the concept of the world? And this slide is basically for you to kind of contemplate that how, when we have a particular philosophy about a particular thing, how it conceptualizes the psychology further. So, like, Locke.
Dr. Karan Mittal: John Locke said that a person is born like a clean blank slate, tabular assault. He said that whatever, when a child is born, he's like a blank slate, and everything can be… can be, you know, taught to the child. But can that… that definition define why a child has a particular liking or a dislike as he… as he grows up?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Particularly for food, some kind of clothes, some attractions, some kind of, you know, avoidances. So can John Locke's definition fit fully into defining a human being?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Khan said that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or maybe even… even… even Descartes said that, like Aspiracy said, that I think, therefore, I am. So is it that if, when you stop thinking, when you are in a deep meditative state, when you're not thinking, the human ceases to exist?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, whatever is your conceptualization about yourself, mind, and the world kind of determines how the further flow happens about these psychological concepts.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Khan says that mind is like a filter. So, when does this filter become active?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Is it active right from the birth? Or the first few years, you can kind of change the filter, and then it becomes more rigid. So all these definitions of mind kind of determine how psychology evolved in the Western world. And one of the reasons that we are covering this in short is, like, you'll have to understand that everyone is trying to explain mind, but in their own, you know, in their own, probably circles, or in their own
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of constrictions. There's not a yaka, there's not a large definition of mind that can explain probably the meditative state also, a child having likes and dislikes also, you having certain inhibitions and attractions also. So, these definitions have… doing their part, but they cannot define the human beings, all the experiences that we see.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then, eventually, we get to the modern psychotherapists, like Freud, Jung, and the modern psychology. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, if you see Freud, Freud said that everything that we do is a result of one of our unconscious experiences. Now, Freud's definition comes very closer to the concepts of vastinal and Sanskaras, but again, it goes only on the pathological terms. Like, if a child did this, and also, Freud made it very sexual and all that stuff. So, Freud gave a definition, so everyone was now covering, you know, small, small, small, small parts.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Freud had a more enlarged definition which went more deeper.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Freud's definition kind of close… comes closer to how we analyze our Chaitanman, Chaitanman, that is conscious space, subconscious space, unconscious space. And then Jung went a step further. Jung also took in the culture, like, now if you… if you see Carl Jung's work, Carl Jung talks about anahar Chakra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: He talks about the heart being the center of psychological thinking. He doesn't talk about mind being somewhere in the brain. He says, whatever transformation happens in the person, the soul transformation happens at the Anna had chakra. He talks about two missions, he talks about different images in his cultures. So he started bringing this element of culture and metaphors and, you know, the social upbringing into psychology. And today's modern psychology definitely
Dr. Karan Mittal: there is… they have taken elements from all these things, but still, when we treat the patients, like, suppose if I belong to the Freudian School of Psychology, I will still see the person only from a subconscious space.
Dr. Karan Mittal: only from the inhibitions, attractions, and tests. If I belong to probably a behavioral school of therapy, I will… like, my hands are moving like this, I am making a bed stamp, I'm sleeping at that particular time, so I will see a person only from the behavior. So, though they tried to explain many different… but there were many definitions of mind that came up, there was no cumulative integrative definition that could kind of determine the whole flow of integrative psychology in the Western world.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Even today, when I belong to a particular school of thought, I stick to that particular school of thought. I might not take in a person as a whole, I might not take… I suppose a person is having issues at home, so… so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I'll give you an example. So I had a small 9, 9, 10-year-old girl that came to me for psychological counseling, and this girl was showing habits of, you know, being very organized in school. Very organized, like, pathologically organized. The pencil has to be like this, the back has to be like this, the books have to be like this. So everything was very organized in a lifetime.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, a normal psychologist might think from autistic spectrum disorder, there are different pathologies that might sound like that, but when we started seeing it from an integrated perspective, when I took a family history, I found out that the fam… the parents were trying to… were getting divorced, like, there were lots of fights, and they were getting separated. Now, this girl.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Felt that
Dr. Karan Mittal: At home, I cannot control anything, because whatever is happening is beyond my control, my age, my authority, etc. So, psychologically, she started controlling things that were under her control, whether it's keeping books, pencils, etc. So, how important it is to see a person in his environment
Dr. Karan Mittal: In his whole totality, in his social background, like, customs and, you know, the socioeconomic background also plays a very important role when you are trying to look at a person.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so… so the modern psychology still has many definitions, but there's no operating system that kind of combines all these systems, and then diagnosis, as well as does the treatment.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so yes, Reju.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, when we study, the Dharmic principles.
GOVINDA Das: You know, the three layers of human existence, right?
GOVINDA Das: The first one is, I will go other way around, third, second, and one.
GOVINDA Das: Biology.
GOVINDA Das: What is the biology? Biology of life is?
GOVINDA Das: The foundation is stay alive.
GOVINDA Das: and function.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Existence comes first.
GOVINDA Das: It doesn't matter who we are, whether you are elevated spiritualist.
GOVINDA Das: Or your noise in spirituality, existence becomes most important primary goal.
GOVINDA Das: Whether you're staying in Vrindavan, staying in Mayapur, staying in Kolkata, what do you need? You need a place to stay, a right kind of room.
GOVINDA Das: functioning restroom.
GOVINDA Das: Functioning electricity.
GOVINDA Das: If it is not functioning properly, what happens?
GOVINDA Das: Even a highly… Evolved soul finds some kind of disturbance.
GOVINDA Das: It is but natural.
GOVINDA Das: Right, therefore, Please understand, this is so important, that
GOVINDA Das: Staying alive and functioning is the biological platform.
GOVINDA Das: And if this is continuously disturbed, it is very difficult for someone to have a stable mind.
GOVINDA Das: You cannot undo this. It does not matter however long you try to…
GOVINDA Das: take counseling from a counselor or a spiritual counselor. When your biological need is disturbed, Unless you fix it.
GOVINDA Das: in the Mahabharat, Our Shamikar Rishi.
GOVINDA Das: He also met with Yudhistil.
GOVINDA Das: In their meeting, he explained there are 3 kinds of medicines.
GOVINDA Das: There is Adi Bhuta, Adi Tayiva, and Adi Atma.
GOVINDA Das: He said, for Adi Bhuta, the matter, what is the medicine? The medicine… Is basically physical reality.
GOVINDA Das: If you are hungry, you need food.
GOVINDA Das: If you're sleepy, you need to sleep, and to sleep, you need some good space.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: That is Adi Huta.
GOVINDA Das: Adi daiva, where you deal with the mind.
GOVINDA Das: That is the mental health.
GOVINDA Das: And atyatma is the spiritual health. They are not separate from each other. They will always exist simultaneously, all the time, depending upon which one needs to have, the counselor has to give an emphasis.
GOVINDA Das: So that is a biological reality.
GOVINDA Das: And the psychology, the experience layer. Connect, engage, and adapt.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Being a biological being, we have to live in a society.
GOVINDA Das: A society could be up 2 people, 40 people, 400 people, right?
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, my question, which I asked, About what are you now?
GOVINDA Das: What you have become, and how you have landed there.
GOVINDA Das: There is a huge influence of the society when I ask this question to myself. Who am I?
GOVINDA Das: If I'm part of a spiritual organization, I will tell I'm a servant of God.
GOVINDA Das: I'm a part of another spiritual organization, I may say aham Brahman.
GOVINDA Das: I am part of another spiritual culture. I may say I am the servant of Jesus.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: So, my identity changes according to my connection.
GOVINDA Das: If I'm born in India, I'm born in Karnataka, I will say I'm Karnatiga.
GOVINDA Das: Within Karnatiga, then I have my Jati also.
GOVINDA Das: Write my region also.
GOVINDA Das: So imagine how many… Layers define our identity when it comes to connection.
GOVINDA Das: We will discuss the Pancha Kosha. There is Anna, prana, Mano. Manomay Kosh is the kosher of the relationship. This is part of our 10-hour session, maybe the last session, right? The Manomay Kosha defines our identity beyond my own identity. I generally ask.
GOVINDA Das: You know, especially, you know, very responsible women. Who are you?
GOVINDA Das: You can see, even if they're educated highly, consciously and unconsciously, they identify their own self in regards to their children, their husband, or their parents.
GOVINDA Das: Think about it. Therefore, this… the experience layer, the connect, engage, and adapt.
GOVINDA Das: That is the second layer.
GOVINDA Das: And then Thharma.
GOVINDA Das: Now, Dharma is different from religion.
GOVINDA Das: One of the greatest tragedy in a Baharatiya knowledge system, Indian knowledge system.
GOVINDA Das: is the lack of understanding of Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: Even if you see the TV debates and others also, oh, we don't follow Dharma, we are not interested in Dharma. Dharma is… it's not part of the secular.
GOVINDA Das: Right, Dharma is all about right alignment.
GOVINDA Das: It is the universal law.
GOVINDA Das: It is also the personal law. It identifies me.
GOVINDA Das: It identifies the universe. It is beyond any kinds of prejudice.
GOVINDA Das: We'll discuss that. Therefore, Dharma gives the right alignment. These are the three existence, and that is what a Baharatiya knowledge system offers all the three unlike
GOVINDA Das: Again, in the Western psychology, as Dr. Karan was mentioning, even Sigmund Freud and Carl Jung have contributed greatly
GOVINDA Das: We do not cancel everything. If you're a counselor, it is not that you have to give up what you have done. You have to align with the Bharatiya, which are dhara. When you align between what is good, which is coming from wherever it comes, because it is knowledge.
GOVINDA Das: And then the foundational idea of Indian knowledge system, when they are integrated properly.
GOVINDA Das: then you become a Dharmic counselor. You may not put a board there. Hopefully, in the future, it should happen. I'm a Dharmic counselor. That means I have the profession.
GOVINDA Das: of MA?
GOVINDA Das: But that is flavored with proper foundational dharma. So these are the three realities. Man first needs to survive.
GOVINDA Das: Then he has to seek meaning.
GOVINDA Das: And ultimately, he has to seek right alignment. These are the foundational idea of IKS.
GOVINDA Das: Next.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah. So, even, I'll just add, Proji, so if you see, the biology part is the physics, you know, it's the material world, and Dharma becomes the metaphysics.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And the mind is the connecting link between the physics and the metaphysics. So now if a client comes to you, and he is in a chronic pain, the physics is a problem, the material reality is a problem, and then you tell him to take the, you know, take the shelter of the metaphysics, it won't happen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Or, if you tell him… or if the mind is a problem, he has many other problems, etc. So, even when the mind is not stable, the metaphysics won't happen. So, kind of clearing this part, the physical part and the mental part, then finally leads to metaphysics. So, it's a hierarchy. You cannot separate
Dr. Karan Mittal: either of it, and say, okay, if, you know, the metaphysics is sorted, the mind will automatically follow, and the body will automatically follow, and no, it won't happen that way. And…
Dr. Karan Mittal: The similar model was also given by Abraham Maslow. Abraham Maslow was a transpersonal psychologist, and he defined the five human needs. The first is the physical need, that is Routi Kapra Makan. Then were the security needs, in a sense, having a job, a social security.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Love and belonging, self-esteem, and then self-actualization, that we can term as, you know, kind of attaining the best version of yourself, that is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably, in spiritual terms, it could be dharma, moksha, stable mind, whatever. So that's self-actualization. Now, you cannot try to kind of satisfy one need by going to the higher need.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You have to work on this need first.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then, go to the second and third game. What we do is we try to kind of settle the level 2 and 3 by telling the person to focus on level 1. It's a struggle. Person cannot do that so easily. So first, work on the mind and the materiality. Third will automatically, as a flow, will be realized.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is about the Descartes split, like, the Western… Western…
Dr. Karan Mittal: psychology basically operated on the function of the Cartesian dual. We, in philosophy, we call it as the Cartesian dual, where we separate the mind and the body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, seeing it from an Indic lens, Vyashti and Samashti, like, we have… we also have splits, like… like, we can separate the two. What it helps with
Dr. Karan Mittal: It helps us in a better understanding of the two. Like, when we see bodies separately, it gives us modern medicine, it gives us science, it gives us all the Pratakshrahmanas, it gives all the physical laws that exist.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? But what it takes away from us is the holistic view. This is how the mind influences the body, and vice versa.
Dr. Karan Mittal: What we talk about today, about the psychosomatic illnesses, or psychosomatic diseases, like, many diseases today are said to be psychosomatic. Even the modern medicine and psychology are trying to believe… are now kind of believing that, that diseases like IBS is a psychosomatic, where your digestive system, because of the constant stress, starts reacting to the stress, because the intestine and the brain are connected with each other.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, also, if there is something called a psychosomatic disease, why can't there be something called a psychosomatic wellness? That if your mind is good, your body automatically starts falling. If you're stress-free, automatically the body will start healing itself better. So, the Dakartan split, or the Cartesian Dual, it gives us the Vashti Sadhna, in the sense it helps us understand both in separate ways.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But what it takes away from us is the samashti, or the sum… or the integration of both, and how both function in reality.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Or how both are interconnected to each other. So when we talk from an Indic lens, we don't see
Dr. Karan Mittal: when a client comes to us, we don't see just the mind, or when, as a doctor, we just don't see the body. If a person is suffering from a chronic disease, it's also essential to see how the mind is working, because the mind is definitely getting affected by the chronic disease, and vice versa. So when we start seeing a person as a whole, in his old totality, like we've probably said, we'll be covering punch kosher, when we start
Dr. Karan Mittal: Seeing the emotions, when you start seeing the thoughts, when you start seeing what's happening at the material level. The amount of interventions we can do, or the amount of help we can offer to the patient or the client, improves, and the results are also faster.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, seeing in split is essential. We don't discard Western psychology, it has given us tools, but also seeing it as a whole. I say holistic is W-H-O-L-I-S-I-T-C. So, so that's holistic, like, seeing both as a whole is equally important.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And therefore, if we see our Rishi's perspective, our Rishis never separated the shareil and Manas. They saw it together. In fact, the definition of
Dr. Karan Mittal: swastya that's given by Sushrutta, Marshi Sushruta, also has the personna Chikta Atma Indri.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when a person has to be defined as a whole, or as healthy, he also needs to have a person, a happy mind, a happy chitra, and also happy senses. The senses also need to be kind of happy in the sense, not too much of deprivation and not too much of indulgence. So, senses also need to operate Hindu.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And that's why our definition of swastya, or swastya, was always being situated in oneself.
Dr. Karan Mittal: being situated in a true nature. And how did we define true nature? Sachitta Ananda. So, if you're not happy, then you're not helped. So, being… so our definition of swastya is swastya, being situated in your true nature. Anything that takes you away from your true nature.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's not the healthy stick. So, when a client comes to us, whether it's a physical issue, mental issue, emotional issue, etc, we also see how much is the happiness quotient, how much is the
Dr. Karan Mittal: feeling happy on a day-to-day basis, week-to-week basis, month-to-month basis. Of course, because of the chronic disease, constant happiness is not possible, but is he doing anything that makes him happy on a daily basis? Is he doing anything that makes him happy on a weekly basis? Because these small doses of happiness helps him kind of get situated in his true nature, in his true self, and that helps us kind of, you know, retrieve that client back, or
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of help the client back to move away from this pathology. So most of the times, when we talk about happiness quotient, or Anandai Pusha, or when we give homeworks to the client, one of the homeworks is also make a list
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of things that make you happy. So I'm working with a female in her 40s.
Dr. Karan Mittal: no particular issue as such, but… but not being able to feel happy on a date. Like… like, she's… she… she… when I told her to write things that makes her feel happy, it took her 3 weeks to get with 2 or 3 things, like walking in the garden, and probably playing, you know, gelling with kids, like playing with kids.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That was the… it took us 3 weeks to get to a list that can she do… that she can do to kind of, you know, feel that happiness on a day-to-day basis. So sometimes you have lost our, you know, maybe… maybe you could take this exercise for yourself. What are the things that make you feel happy? Do you have 5, 6, 7, 8, 10 things that you… and also, how much you do these things on a regular basis?
Dr. Karan Mittal: One of the reasons why we have developed exercises in this module is also exercise… individual exercises, and also exercises in pairs, groups, sharing, is one of the traits, or one of the, one of the requirements to become a good counselor is to feel vulnerable.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or to know how it feels to sit on that side of the chair.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So when you develop these, when you work on your concepts, when you work on your beliefs, when you work on your judgments and issues, you feel that vulnerability. And when you feel that vulnerability, you know how the client opposite will feel. Earlier, two decades ago, psychology was about the psychologist sitting on a pedestal.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And from that pedestal, the psychologist, you know, kind of commanded, you know, that body language, and then writing with a pen on a note. That was… that was the concept of psychologists. But now, eventually, the psychology is more about being at the same resonance with the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also, experiencing what the client experienced. Probably, the client has depression, I have not felt that depression in my life. But I should know how it feels to sit on that side of the chair, share your inner, inner dark secrets, or inner inhibitions, or inner issues. That helps us become more empathetic.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, nowadays, if you see the modern psychological trainings make it compulsory for the trainers or for the evolving therapists to undergo sessions themselves. They make group exercises, pair exercises, triad exercises, fumble study, because they have to work on their judgment also. Suppose if I have a judgment.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That mind is something that can be tamed. Suppose I have a belief that mind can be tamed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Every counselli that is sitting in front of me, anything he talks about the mind, I'll be operating from that judgment.
Dr. Karan Mittal: This is a small thing, and this is not a big thing. That small thing for me because of my belief system.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But how big is for that client? That vulnerability is lost. So that's why the exercises designed here are to kind of make you understand what that vulnerability is, and also work on your judgments, your beliefs, your ecosystem within. That will help
Dr. Karan Mittal: you become a better. So, next time when you're talking to a counselor of yours, because most of you are spiritual mentors.
Dr. Karan Mittal: When you're making an analysis, you also analyze from what belief system are you operating this analysis on.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, or what… if you're advising a client, what belief system makes you advise the client on that?
Dr. Karan Mittal: That will help you take yourself a level deeper within, as well as a counselor.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, the split between, like, what we saw as the Cartesian duality, or the split between body and mind, we never saw it in the Indian tradition. In Indian tradition, everything was taken as a whole.
Dr. Karan Mittal: A way they used to see all the… the way the… like, now, suppose the psychologist
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry, a client walks into my room, the way they will start seeing from the way he's walking, the way he's sitting, the way he's talking, all these things are analyzed. We never… it's not like, okay, the client just sat over here and now starts speaking. What is your problem? What are the issues? Who are there in the family? It's not like history-taking.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you see the person as a whole, because these things give you an indication of what might be, you know, happening in his life, or in his society, or in his individual, personal issues. So we saw a person as a whole. Now, even if you see
Dr. Karan Mittal: the kosher theory. All the punch koshas
Dr. Karan Mittal: are definitely seen separately, but in a Jiva, we consider them to be one together, and we analyze the thoughts, we analyze the emotions, we analyze the partnership tree, and finally, we also analyze the physical body. And that gives us a clarity of what's happening. So, for an example,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Suppose I'm… I'm… I'm a wife here, and I'm kind of treating a person with hyperacidity. Now, it's easy for me to prescribe sushikaras, or pantocid, or any of these diseases to curb that acidity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But when I ask the… ask the primary the history of the client, then I'll come to know that he's in a corporate job, probably CEO of some…
Dr. Karan Mittal: particular, particular company. There's lots of politics that's going on. That increases the stress. The stress is now happening in the thoughts that will affect
Dr. Karan Mittal: the emotions that will affect the pranesharina, and finally it will start affecting the share. This is one of the most gross examples of a psychosomatic disease that will take. So, they will analyze, or in the council will analyze from all these
Dr. Karan Mittal: 4 layers. And he will know where to put a stop.
Dr. Karan Mittal: He'll probably tell him a few exercises to work on his thoughts.
Dr. Karan Mittal: He'll give him a few exercises to kind of work on the emotions, a few exercises to work on the pranasheer, like regulating the prana, the habits, the schedule, and finally.
Dr. Karan Mittal: For the time being, we'll give medicines to curb the acidity, and then eventually these things will start taking over the healing of the heart.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So we saw the person as a group. We never saw the person as one independent, faculty, like mine, or the emotions, or the public. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: As a counselor, you don't split. You start integrating. So next time someone comes to, take sessions or counseling from you, it's not just the problem that we are discussing, we are healing the person. So we discuss a bit of his family life, a bit of his social life, material life, and then see where is the root cause for the problem lie.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Would you like to add something?
GOVINDA Das: To add, yeah, just to add.
GOVINDA Das: You know, there are 3 things, Sharira, Jiwa, and Atma.
GOVINDA Das: Now, the Sharidah is the body made of Pancha Mahabhat.
GOVINDA Das: earth, water, fire, air, ether. That is called a share.
GOVINDA Das: And then Jiva is what… Jeeva is basically the body.
GOVINDA Das: earth, water, fire, air, ether, mind, intelligence, and ego.
GOVINDA Das: Including the Atma, that is called as Jiva.
GOVINDA Das: Very important to understand. See, our… our rishis.
GOVINDA Das: They had a brilliant way of explaining. While they would explain, therefore they defined Sankeshastra.
GOVINDA Das: Sankesh Shastra means explaining everything minutely.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: But that same Sankesh Shastra, while explaining minutely.
GOVINDA Das: the rishis, the Ayurvedic people, or the rishis, They were extremely…
GOVINDA Das: Learn it in regards to integrating the application.
GOVINDA Das: Varanan keile, sang ke hai, application ke liy, samagarata hai.
GOVINDA Das: You know, I need to… I'll translate it, those who don't understand.
GOVINDA Das: Explanation requires Sankhya.
GOVINDA Das: But application requires Samagrata.
GOVINDA Das: No, there is no Kanda Kanda.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, so therefore, again, our, Pancho Kosher. Punchakosh, we will discuss that also.
GOVINDA Das: Generally, the Panchakos is defined, or Anama is the lowest, and Anandma is the highest.
GOVINDA Das: We do not go in hierarchy. That is not step 1, step 2, step 3, step 4, step 5.
GOVINDA Das: The Bharate Kon is always the circular Dhrushti kon, please understand.
GOVINDA Das: It is not… it is not, you know, like a staircase. It is like a, you know, semicircular thing continuously moving.
GOVINDA Das: Till the last breath, one needs to focus on the Annamay Kosh.
GOVINDA Das: In fact, as a man or a woman becomes old, they focus more on their food.
GOVINDA Das: what to eat, what not to eat, how much to eat, how much not to eat. If there is some disturbance in the food, their entire system gets jeopardized.
GOVINDA Das: Right? It is not that because you become spiritually elevated, suddenly you become reckless in regards to your food habits.
GOVINDA Das: So the anamaya remains, and within that Anna Maya, there could be… in that anna only, there could be a prana. In that anna, there could be mano, because who has cooked it?
GOVINDA Das: In that Anna only, there could be Buddhi, Vikyanmay kosher, and that Anna itself, there could be Anandamaya. So every kosher, every aspect has all other aspects in regards to application. Only in regards to explanation, we
GOVINDA Das: do use Sankya. So, therefore, as Karanji was mentioning.
GOVINDA Das: That analysis will always be Sankhya, application will always be yoga.
GOVINDA Das: integrated.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, next.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also,
Dr. Karan Mittal: the whole philosophy operates from the Yat Pinde Takra… sorry, Yad Brahmandita Pinde, like, whatever is in the universe kind of starts reflecting into your body. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when we analyze a person, like, if you even study Ayurveda, Ayurveda starts from… it doesn't start from understanding the body. It starts from understanding the universe and the cosmos first. And then it comes down to understanding the body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, if you have… if you kind of skip either of the two, it will start impacting the way you understand the person, or you understand the universe. So, you have to… when you understand the person, you have to understand his universe. In the sense, what I meant to say was you have to start with understanding his universe. That could be things around him.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The emotions, the thoughts, and then finally come to the issue that we're going to address.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In that question. So, before we go ahead, I would like you to kind of just do a small exercise and just close your eyes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… and just be as relaxed as possible. We are coming back to the first question that we
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably started the session with… And I will take that slide later, so that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, we can just focus on yourself, just focus on your…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Body, or whatever, just close your eyes and just focus on any one thing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… just… For a moment, Just see where is your mind?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Where would you localize your mind in the body?
Dr. Karan Mittal: There's no right or wrong as an answer.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just try to be aware. Where is your mind? Are you able to localize it to a position, a geography, a location?
Dr. Karan Mittal: I agree.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'll not give too much time to this question, but I want you to kind of now
Dr. Karan Mittal: Think of a happy memory.
Dr. Karan Mittal: With your eyes closed, think of a happy memory, maybe the most happiest, or maybe the happiest memory that you can think of today.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And as you bring that memory to… bring that memory to your consciousness, just be aware of your body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Where do you feel that happiness?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just go into that memory as vividly as possible, as live as possible, and then see where did you feel that happiness in your body?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And again, I want you to move to another memory, probably a negative memory, a sad memory.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And see, where do you locate that sadness in your world.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if you're done, you can open your eyes. We'll go into a deeper version of the exercise in one of the future sessions on how to work with these memories. But… but I want you to come up with how did you feel? Like, just the three names, like, where did you feel your mind, your happiness, and your… probably the negative emotion? Any one of you could share, probably.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If at all you felt it.
Aarti Ganesh: I would like to share, Pragujit.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. Yes, my decision.
Aarti Ganesh: The negative emotion was strongly felt in my feet, I don't know for what reason.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Aarti Ganesh: And the positive emotion was felt in my heart.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Beautiful.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, it's not enough. Anyone else would like to share?
Dr. Karan Mittal: As I said, this is a safe space, and opening up
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's also part of being willing to, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I usually feel another happiness in my chest, and whenever there's sadness, it happens in my top. This is how my body functions. Anyone else?
Renuka Bhuta: I would like to share, Prabhuji.
Renuka Bhuta: Oh, happiness was in the heart.
Renuka Bhuta: And, sadness, somewhere it went, into my mind.
Renuka Bhuta: But I couldn't connect it all that much.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sure, sure. The reason or the purpose of this exercise was if mind was only metaphysical, was just a construct, then why are you feeling your emotions in your heart, your abdomen, your feet?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And if the mind is fully physical, then why it changes for everybody?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And that's where the somatic version, or seeing the body and the mind as a whole, comes together. That everyone feels some or the other emotion in different parts of the body. Like, I feel it in my chest, abdomen, someone said feet and the chest.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And someone said shoulders. So, different emotions kind of are stored in different, different areas of our body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if the whole body is accessible, or is available for different emotions, where does the mind lack?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's the question that… and, like, if you go to seek… read Sushuta, Sushutra Marsha Sushut said that the mind is in the heart.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In fact, he has called it as a major strutas, in the sense, manowah Struthas. This is the mind starts in the heart, and then there are… there are nadis that run over and take this… the faculties of the mind to different parts of the body. But what modern medicine says, mind lies over here.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But when you feel it, the emotions can be all over the body. So where do you understand the mind to be?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if you cannot localize a mile, then how would you treat it?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, that's where is the strict. So if you go from a neuroscience perspective, or from just a pure neurologic perspective, this is the mind, the brain is the mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I analyze mind, whether it's anxiety, depression, OCD, schizophrenia, everything from the brain's perspective.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But anxious person, when he's anxious, doesn't feel the emotion here. He feels the gabarat or the anxiety over here.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So how do I address this and this? That's the split.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or, when a person comes to depression, I'm treating the neurotransmitter here, but the person is coming with this, mindset where… sorry, this body position where his, you know, shoulders are down, his head is down, he's wanting to sleep, that's happening all in the body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, it's not that this is wrong. This is good. This… working on the brain, or working on that neurochemical organ or the physical organ is needed. In fact, Arishi's in Ayurveda, when we talk about
Dr. Karan Mittal: healing the psychological diseases. They talk about three chikitsas. They talk about Yukti Vapashri, that is, using medicines, etc. They talk about safarabhajay Chikitsa, that is counseling and practices, and they talk about Devi Vapashri Chikitza, that is, rituals and customs and everything that helps.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Harish, he's never separated that, okay, if you're coming to a psychiatrist.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you will just take medicines, and you will… other things won't work. If you're coming to, probably, a Jyotesha, you just do the pujas, and you just do the rituals, and just do the… whatever, japas, etc, and other things are not okay. They said you have to work on all the three aspects. They never separated at all.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so when we look, the way… the way you locate your mind in different parts of your body, or your different belief systems, the way… that is the way that kind of helps you evolve this theory of mind, the understanding of mind, the diagnosis, and the further that you go. So neuroscience just looks over here, so it will work only over here.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Freud looked at the mind, and it's only metaphysical part that is just working on the unconscious, subconscious, and all these conscious minds. So he just worked in talking, talking, talking, talking, talking, and trying to kind of uncover the layers of the mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And behavior just sees behavior, so just… just kind of correcting the behavior changes the mind. But all these are the parts of the analogy that, you know, that in India, or many other parts of the world.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We are seeing just the parts of the elephant, or we are just touching the parts of the elephant, but IKS teaches us to kind of go a few steps back and see the whole elephant, and then you will locate which part is the problem.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so combining all these, you cannot say that chanting and meditation will mean everything else. You cannot say, just go to the counselor, chanting meditation is not okay. You can't say just wake up at 5am, regularize your schedule, and everything else will follow you. You have to take 30, 33, 33, 33%, and then make it better.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Doji, would you like to add something to this?
GOVINDA Das: Thank you. Did you touch upon the neuroscience to touch the brain?
Dr. Karan Mittal: I bet… I did it a bit privy, but if you could add here. Yeah.
GOVINDA Das: So basically, again, like as…
GOVINDA Das: You know, again, our focus has been…
GOVINDA Das: Integrating everything, and that is what we want to provide to the people who are supposed to counsel, whether they're children, professional counselees, or spiritual counselees.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: sometimes, what we do not focus, especially in Bharatvishi.
GOVINDA Das: That those who practice spirituality, they undermine the physical layers of reality.
GOVINDA Das: And those who are hardcore materialistic, they undermine the spiritual practices.
GOVINDA Das: those who are practicing half-baked Ayurved, they will… Slander the modern medicine.
GOVINDA Das: And the modern medicine people, even having the name Tripati, Trivedi, Shukla, Mishra.
GOVINDA Das: Right? They are… the name suggests they are supposed to be knowing the Vedas.
GOVINDA Das: But there are highly sophisticated doctors.
GOVINDA Das: And they are a huge issue with the… Bharatiya Vichard Hara.
GOVINDA Das: Alright.
GOVINDA Das: So therefore, again, when we go back to the Bharti, which are the IKS, the Indian Knowledge System.
GOVINDA Das: Like, this neuroscience.
GOVINDA Das: There is a book also which discusses
GOVINDA Das: Even… even some part of your neurology is disturbed. It does not simply Disturb your physical functioning.
GOVINDA Das: It disturbs your emotional functioning also.
GOVINDA Das: And they're a purely physical part, they're Prateksha pramana. They may be very, very delicate, but they're still gross, and that gross particles
GOVINDA Das: Have the power to disturb our relationship and our mindset also.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, so therefore, you know, the… our rishis, like in the Ayurved.
GOVINDA Das: A regular applying of the oil.
GOVINDA Das: Right? The mother would apply the oil on the head of a child.
GOVINDA Das: a continual massage to the brain every day before the snar. Some would do apply after the San.
GOVINDA Das: What kind of impact it created, we have no clue, because we did not
GOVINDA Das: had an issue of disturbing our mind. Disturbing our brain, and through that, disturbing our mind.
GOVINDA Das: There was much more stability.
GOVINDA Das: Right? The whole concept of avatar, the whole concept of avatar…
GOVINDA Das: Whenever there's a disturbance in what? Disturbance in wholesome living.
GOVINDA Das: Dharma is wholesome living. When that becomes… less…
GOVINDA Das: Dharma becomes prevalent, artificial living becomes prevalent.
GOVINDA Das: Even an avatar, why would he come to this material world if it is not so relevant and it is not so important?
GOVINDA Das: Right, so therefore, the Rishidrishti, the Bharati Adarshti.
GOVINDA Das: The way the Darshti is integrating even the most subtle part of our brain
GOVINDA Das: towards 2 also, and only when we deal with the body. I remember talking to an Ayurvedic doctor. He explained very, very easily.
GOVINDA Das: He said you can only transcend your body when you have no bodily issue, and he gave an example that if your knee is hurting.
GOVINDA Das: You cannot say, I'm not Disney.
GOVINDA Das: You can give a lecture saying that I'm not this body, I'm the spirit soul, but you would be looking at doctor immediately after the function is over, or your talk is over.
GOVINDA Das: So the point is…
GOVINDA Das: Again, integrating, and the entire knowledge system helps us to integrate, and that's what we have also designed our app also.
GOVINDA Das: To help us integrate in every aspect.
GOVINDA Das: this pattern. Next one.
Dr. Karan Mittal: As I think, Vershe Sushut speaks, Sharir Ramadhyam Galu, Kalu Dharma Sadhna. Sharir is the only instrument that can help you sadhday or thharu.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we'll be getting into an exercise, and this exercise will also involve working in pairs. So, I want you to write
Dr. Karan Mittal: Three beliefs that you have about mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And kind of categorize these three beliefs, or these three beliefs, into four categories, academic, personal, cultural, and unknown.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also, first you do that, and then I'll be kind of putting you all into breakout rooms. Breakout room is you work in a pair with a partner, and that partner is randomly selected. And you share how these beliefs have kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: changed the way you look at things, or has affected you. Like, suppose if I feel that mind can be tamed, then I have kind of either stressed to myself too much when things were not doing good.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or it could be a positive thing also, could be a negative thing also. It could be stressing myself too much. Second could be when there were small, small issues, etc, I kind of tamed my mind into being more productive, or more, like, more… more functional. So, I want you to write three beliefs that you have about mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this is one of the preliminary exercises that we do when we take transpersonal psychology. So… and then, right, classify the beliefs, and in the pair, you share it with your partner. That's the beginning of being well equipped to someone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So yes, I'll just give you 5 minutes till I make the breakout rooms, and then… then you have to just join the breakout rooms. I'll give you 10 minutes, 5 minutes on each side, like, 5 minutes you share, and the 5 minutes the partner shares.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also, to make it a just bit more intense and complicated, if it's possible, when someone is speaking, also be aware of what belief system or judgment you are making about
Dr. Karan Mittal: the opposite person's belief system. That will make it more intense for them.
GOVINDA Das: So this is, about the… what they've learned academically about the mind?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, different.
GOVINDA Das: Culturally about the mind?
GOVINDA Das: Third is what they've learned personally about the mind, and fourth is unknown, right? This is what the… Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, suppose I have three beliefs. Suppose one is, like, my mind can be tamed and mine is just an instrument, so it can come from a culture or from a teacher. It could be my mind, kind of.
Dr. Karan Mittal: overreacts when I try to suppress it more, that could be my personal belief that I have understood by experience. So, just… just try to kind of get into the experiencing it, working on… working on yourself, and then we'll take it forward.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Miss… So, 5 minutes, and then 10 minutes of spare exercise.
Vikram Chakilam: Probably I never thought about the mind, or… I don't know what to write beliefs about the mind, I never thought about it, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I'll help you a bit. What is mine for you?
Vikram Chakilam: where, thoughts generate. That's all I… I was assuming. I don't know anything about that more than enough.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, minds are just a place where thoughts generate. How have you kind of got to that belief system? Is it academic, someone told you? Is it cultural that you have understood from scriptures, etc? Or you still don't know what exactly it is?
Vikram Chakilam: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So maybe that's unknown. Yeah. So now I want you to under… now I want you to contemplate a bit deeper, and just go into the perspective of
Dr. Karan Mittal: Mind is just thoughts. How has it affected Vikram?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, are you too aware of your thoughts? Do you discard your thoughts or not? Has it helped you with your sadhana and your family? So, how that belief system has affected you?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that will just… it's… because it's a beginner-level exercise, we're not getting very deep into how to do it. Just three beliefs. Probably, then mind is an instrument in the hand of the soul. That comes in cultural beliefs, okay? So then you see how it… yeah, so just… yeah.
Aarti Ganesh: Prabhuji, I have… I have… I have a few statements about mine, but I'm unable to decide if it's going to be fitting under academic, personal, or cultural, so how do I go about.
Dr. Karan Mittal: This… So, can you… if you're okay sharing in the group, can you share it here, Madhasi?
Aarti Ganesh: Yeah, for example, mind is one of the components of your personality.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sure.
Aarti Ganesh: Another statement I have is, mine is what?
Aarti Ganesh: Makes me perceive someone or some situation in a particular way.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Keith?
Aarti Ganesh: The third statement is, mind is what makes me feel.
Aarti Ganesh: So, I don't know where… what goes where.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, mind is what makes you feel. Have you experienced it, or someone told you and you believe it, or it is like you have read it in a scripture, or it has come through your religion, or… how… when did you first experience this mind is what you feel?
Aarti Ganesh: I read about it closely.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, read about it. So it is, it is, it is basically cultural, yeah.
Aarti Ganesh: Oh, okay, okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay. Now, the third step is, mind is what you feel.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, how has it affected you?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Are you, like, when you feel too much, do you try to train your mind in a way?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or when your mind is probably, thinking a lot, are you aware of your thoughts or your emotions? Like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: associating this function of feeling to the mind, how has it impacted you? So, your thoughts are not related to your mind, your body's not related to your mind, like, just be more… I cannot probably suggest how it has affected you, but you just think how this belief starts affecting you.
Aarti Ganesh: Yes, Will, thanks.
A-Suraj Racha: I also had one question, apparently.
A-Suraj Racha: Hello?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
A-Suraj Racha: So…
A-Suraj Racha: In the beginning, we established that our environments also affect the way we think, like, our environments are a factor for our development of the mind. And the second thing, we, like, in a subtle way, also established that
A-Suraj Racha: There is a progressive understanding to mind as well. Like, going towards you was saying there's biology, then there's psychology, and then there's the karma. Now.
A-Suraj Racha: As a person, like, worldwide, there are many ideologies, there are many philosophies, foods of thought.
A-Suraj Racha: Now, one person… So, based on their exposure, the mind is developing.
A-Suraj Racha: how do we take this into account? Because if someone is receiving a progressive thought, then you say, okay, they're fortunate. And if someone is receiving a degrading thought process, or a degrading school of thought, then,
A-Suraj Racha: then, naturally, their mind will go in that direction. So, like, what are the… if you're getting my question, so…
A-Suraj Racha: Basically, what are the… how should we take this into account? Is it just a fortune that, okay, I was exposed to the right philosophy, or I was not exposed to the right understanding?
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's probably the evolved form of getting into your beliefs, Suraji. Like, how do you perceive the whole thing?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Right now, the exercise probably is more about
Dr. Karan Mittal: just trying to go a step deeper into analyzing your belief systems. And I specifically took mind because that's the topic we are talking about. You could take any belief system, any belief system about religions, but that would just expand it unnecessarily. But whether it's fortunate, unfortunate, and all that stuff is probably the… looking at mind
Dr. Karan Mittal: different perspectives that probably would come in the later part of the training, I guess.
Renuka Bhuta: I have a question, how do I connect unknown? So, what do we mean by, beliefs about my unknown?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Known as you don't know the source of that belief.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Whether it's personal, social, cultural, you don't know. Where does it come to you from? That's unknown.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Great.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I'll just open the breakout rooms, and at the end of 10 or 12 minutes, I'll just close the breakout rooms. So, if you have 3 participants, you have 4-4 minutes each. If you have 2 participants, you have 10 minutes, 5 minutes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You have to join the breakout room. There will be a pop-up on your screen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just join the precaution.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Guardsian ones, you have not joined.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You're not there to them. Alright.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Listen, 6…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, ma'am.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'm just closing it, in 60 seconds, it'll be a back push. Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I mean, in the meantime, those who have participated, please share our experiences, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How… how was it for you, Vikram J?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe Naji…
Lavina: we tried.
Vikram Chakilam: We're good.
Lavina: So we were introducing each other since we had time to talk, and we learned from each other, like, what are our goals, why are we here? And we spoke about the beliefs. Do we need to discuss about my beliefs?
Lavina: Okay, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just the experiences, man. Whatever you feel about.
Lavina: I learned a lot from, the Prabhuji. He's a, you know, he's a counselor for couples, but he has some insecurity about how to train with, you know, strain. I learned something, you know. And being… three of us had the same, you know, spoke about, being a devotee, fun.
Lavina: And the… how much knowledge ISCON has given me, and all of them.
Lavina: So we had a short conversation regarding that. It was very nice.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sure. Le Clemdie?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Appreciate it, sir.
Vikram Chakilam: Yeah, actually, Lavinachi has shared everything, actually. We… I felt very good knowing others also.
Vikram Chakilam: I got some inspiration from both, actually.
Vikram Chakilam: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay. Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Do you want to share what is your personal belief, cultural belief, you know, that specific points about the mind?
GOVINDA Das: Anybody wants to…
Lavina: I ain'.
GOVINDA Das: focus at.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's something.
A-Suraj Racha: Yes, I would like to share, one observations, like, in general also.
A-Suraj Racha: Like, many times.
A-Suraj Racha: Just like if we have a specs. So, if we are wearing sunglasses and we see a particular color, I'm wearing one particular specks, if we see a particular color.
A-Suraj Racha: So, similarly, based on how our upbringing has been, or what our thought process has been, so there is always a tendency that
A-Suraj Racha: Any new concept comes in, we will always try to see it through that particular lens only. So, there's a tendency that we narrow ourselves and not accept any new school of thought.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay. What I… yeah, sorry, someone was saying something, yes.
Zoom user: Hi, Krishna, can I tell you?
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: AC assistant.
Zoom user: Yeah,
Zoom user: Academically, I think, we can just say the functions of the mind, but we cannot define it, that mind is like our emotions and feelings.
Zoom user: Towards different situations, and reactions towards that situation.
Zoom user: And, culturally, due to spiritual knowledge, I think mind is like, you know, suksma Sharif within…
Zoom user: Within our… this grass body.
Zoom user: And, personally, I feel that mind is like some other personality within me, which I have to explain that small child within me, through my intelligence, like a mother.
Zoom user: Perfect.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, what I would request all of you is, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Deepen your understanding of how these beliefs impact your… has impacted your life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I would request you all to share it on the group. Like, you don't need to elaborate it much, but it would also help you open up, and it would also encourage other participants to open up and share their beliefs, and it will also give you a database of what are the different beliefs that, you know, clients can come to you with. So it's all in all good for everyone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's how psychology trainings function. You open up in pairs, then you open up in a larger group, and then you open up in even a bigger group. So that's how your ability to handle vulnerability and opening yourself increases. So, thank you, everyone, for sharing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Ravuji, should we take up questions, since we are at the end of programming?
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Our session today, yeah.
GOVINDA Das: Yup.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we… we have a few questions, Provji, which… which are in the chat, maybe related to Dharma, so maybe a few questions.
Vikram Chakilam: source?
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Should I read it for you, Christian?
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Suraj Prabhuji has written, there are many schools of thought which unconsciously teach us to ignore more layer by putting another as more important. Example, spiritual life is more important and ignore desires. So, is it actually possible to… no, so is it possible to actually remove need of one?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or most of the times, it's self-inflicted suffering.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, so in the beginning stages of your… any stage, any philosophy, when you're enthusiastic, you assimilate it.
GOVINDA Das: And try to be adventurous.
GOVINDA Das: You know, and many adventures are very artificial.
GOVINDA Das: They're not natural.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, what is the greatest adventure? The greatest adventure is to realize what you are.
GOVINDA Das: Like, in the fourth cant of the Haggottam, the best example is the example of Dhru.
GOVINDA Das: Now, Dhru was given knowledge by Narut Muni.
GOVINDA Das: To transcend the limitation of his competition with his brother's stepbrother.
GOVINDA Das: And with his stepmother, and the father was not willing to give him a place to sit on his lap.
GOVINDA Das: So, Druva came to achieve something much greater than what his father had, grandfather had.
GOVINDA Das: And the great sage Narath Bune said, no, you should not worry about this, these are all very insignificant things.
GOVINDA Das: Then I should focus on the substance rather than the apparent.
GOVINDA Das: And Drua, interestingly, said, no, I need to also focus on this.
GOVINDA Das: And Narad Muni… Was fascinated by the honesty
GOVINDA Das: and the grounding of Dhruva, he comes back to the father of Dhruva, and appreciates Dhruva's disposition.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: the great Prahlad, for that matter, right? We take these stories, Prahlad.
GOVINDA Das: You know, he certainly spoke to Lord Narsingdev about. He's foundational. Pranhlar means one was naturally happy.
GOVINDA Das: the highest realm of spirituality he experienced with Lord Narsing.
GOVINDA Das: But how did he rule his kingdom? He ruled his kingdom in a very integrated way.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, the Bharatiya, which are Dhara, the Indian knowledge system.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, again, if you study Bhagavad Gita also, the Indian knowledge system does not emphasize one against other unless that one aspect is diseased.
GOVINDA Das: If my buddy has become completely brashed up.
GOVINDA Das: It is not that only Buddhi is brushed. The mind is also gone crazy, the physical self is also gone crazy.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, The emphasis might be there in regards to conversation about the mind.
GOVINDA Das: The emphasis might be there in regards to conversation about disciplining the body.
GOVINDA Das: But the solution, ultimately, is integrated already. So, therefore, it is not possible
GOVINDA Das: In the Sanskrit, it is called as a,
GOVINDA Das: For all problem, one solution doesn't work.
GOVINDA Das: Not possible, non-existent.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And another question by Renu Kaji, how can everyone have similar dharma when entire world is divided on the basis of different dharma? How can counselor connect in such a situation?
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, Dharma is not a religion, Dharma is not faith, Dharma is not… But…
GOVINDA Das: Dharma is the universal law, right? Dharma means fire will burn.
GOVINDA Das: We cannot say, oh, I don't believe fire burns. Whether you are Pakistani, whether you are a Hindustani, whether you are Afghanistani, fire is fire. So when you go settler of the same principle.
GOVINDA Das: If you simply observe, the word Dharma has nothing to do with the religion.
GOVINDA Das: The word Dharma has nothing to do with rituals.
GOVINDA Das: The word Dharma has nothing to do with my faith.
GOVINDA Das: When faith is connected to Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: When rituals are connected to Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: When beliefs are connected to Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: then that kind of understanding gives rise to integration. Therefore, Dharma is universal.
GOVINDA Das: Faith is personal.
GOVINDA Das: Dharma is universal.
GOVINDA Das: Beliefs are cultural, societal, right? Dharma is universal.
GOVINDA Das: The rituals are regional.
GOVINDA Das: Dharma is universal. Language is…
GOVINDA Das: In Karnataka, there is many languages. There is Turu, there is Kannada, there is North Canada, right? Those diversity will be there.
GOVINDA Das: But that is not Dharma. That is one small aspect of Dharma. Therefore, Dharma can always be universal, it has always been universal, it will always be universal.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, foundation has to be Dharva.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, I think Ruthuja has a question.
Rutuja Nayak: Yeah, yes, Guruji. I was, discussing this with, in the room also, that, since we are born, we're always being taught about what is right, what is wrong, good values, bad values, morality, etc.
Rutuja Nayak: I… and whenever you read certain books, or you consume certain kind of content, maybe movies, podcasts, everyone, whenever everyone speaks or writes, it is…
Rutuja Nayak: mostly coming from their own experiences, own, situations, etc. So, be it any philosophers or psychologists, whatever the theories they have.
Rutuja Nayak: which one, I mean, one should follow, because I… personally, I started feeling, you know, in terms of my experience, I think, everything I've… mostly, okay, not everything, mostly I've learned is from my own experiences, my own realizations, etc. So…
Rutuja Nayak: What theory do you exactly follow, if my question makes sense?
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, therefore, we are going to touch upon this, the concept of dharma and karma. Now, the word karma.
GOVINDA Das: You know, like he was mentioning, that ultimately.
GOVINDA Das: Ultimately, when you follow whatever you follow.
GOVINDA Das: In the Dharma tradition, in the Karma tradition, right and wrong is a very superficial reality.
GOVINDA Das: What karma says is the consequences, the action and consequences.
GOVINDA Das: Alright? And therefore, if you study, like, I'm talking with one professor in, in Ayam Ahmedabad.
GOVINDA Das: So, we were discussing about vegetarianism and non-vegetarianism.
GOVINDA Das: Right? One may say, oh, one should not be non-vegetarian.
GOVINDA Das: Like, recently, somebody celebrated their birthday, they went to Kamak, yeah, they freed many animals.
GOVINDA Das: Because animal killing is bad.
Rutuja Nayak: Yeah.
GOVINDA Das: Alright? So, but if you study Bharati Sanskrati.
GOVINDA Das: The great literatures also, they do not create a conflict between vegetarianism and non-vegetarianism.
GOVINDA Das: They create an evolution of lifestyle.
GOVINDA Das: In the Ramayan, there is a description of…
GOVINDA Das: Some of the rishes feeding meat for Ram's army.
GOVINDA Das: Lord Ram himself never ate meat during his 14 years of exile.
GOVINDA Das: So, we were discussing about this. He's a spiritualist also.
GOVINDA Das: Like, there is a debate, oh, all the higher caste are vegetarians, and lower caste are meat-eaters.
GOVINDA Das: Right? There are certain scholars, they talk about it. But if you study India properly, vegetarianism has nothing to do with caste.
GOVINDA Das: In many parts of Maharashtra and Karnataka, even those who are not upper caste, they're pure vegetarians.
GOVINDA Das: If you go to Bengal, if you go to Bihar, if you go to Odisha, even people from Brahman community, not 100, 200 years, in thousand years, they're eating meat.
GOVINDA Das: If you come to South… Kerala, Karnataka, coastal Karnataka, there is a called Sarasak Brahman community.
Rutuja Nayak: I am.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, I know. I know. Right. So, 80% of them they consume.
GOVINDA Das: That does not mean they're, oh, how can they do like that? So please understand, the Bharatiya, which are Dara, yes, when you're part of a group, they make what is rule and what is not a rule. If you're working in a company, they say, this is your uniform.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Because you are a part of that group.
GOVINDA Das: then that becomes right and wrong. If you join one organization, they have their rule.
GOVINDA Das: So they don't claim that these rules have to be followed. Yes, if you're part of that group, then you follow that. So, that is absolute
GOVINDA Das: to the group.
GOVINDA Das: But it is not absolute to the universe.
GOVINDA Das: So that is what we are going to connect also tomorrow, our faith-centric definition of mind.
GOVINDA Das: So the karma definition is very beautiful and very profound. Do I have the power to consume, and do I have the power to digest? The karma theory is that I take responsibility of my actions.
GOVINDA Das: And the consequences. So, therefore, we will study that more and deeper. Karan, you want to add something?
Rutuja Nayak: Thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Dr. Buji, we have a few more questions. Should I just go to them?
GOVINDA Das: Good day.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so, Alessandroji has asked, how can a counselor or anyone helping to aim others develop a holistic understanding of mind across different fields, given that mastering even one of these areas can take a lifetime? So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, how does IKS work, or how does this system work, is you have a broad perspective of what are the elements
Dr. Karan Mittal: that can influence a person, whether it's neuroscience, your written behavior, psychology, Ayurveda. You should know, like, if a person with the pratriti is coming to you, that's a basic thing. What kind of things would work, what kind of things wouldn't work. Like Prabhuji said, like, in Shastras, it's very clear that there's no segregation of vegetarian. It depends on your Prakrati. If a Kshatriya
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably needs to eat, probably, correct me if I'm wrong, it needs to eat non-veg, because he has to develop that aggressiveness, etc, etc. But similarly, so it's having a broad overview of many things, and then you specializing into one or two, three things, and that kind of makes you a better therapist. Even in modern-day therapy, it happens, like, we learn a lot.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then we have a few, techniques or therapies that we specialize in that helps
Dr. Karan Mittal: us in understanding the patient better as a broad perspective, and then doing our interventions in that micro-perspective of hope therapy. Pranayim is the only way to empower Pranh Shakti, also what degrades Pran Shakti. When we do Pranhai Kosher, we'll discuss that, Shubamji.
GOVINDA Das: Just, just to add, what, Karanji said, with that for Alex, Alex's question. See, when you become specialized in your field.
GOVINDA Das: You do not undermine other fields. The problem is not specialization. The problem is undermining other field.
GOVINDA Das: If you're specialized as a neurosurgeon.
GOVINDA Das: You cannot say, oh, what is this, you know, applying oil on the head and doing massage? That is bogus. So that becomes arrogance based upon their specialization. So I can be ignorant about other fields.
GOVINDA Das: But at least I should be knowing very well, other fields also have something tangible, and therefore, I'm good in this, but you can also work on this with other experts.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe Jitindaji's question. Jitindaji mind exists in which part of the body? This is a debate that happens in different schools of philosophy for the same thing, like Atma.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You cannot pinpoint mind to a particular part of the body. That's the wholesome understanding of ICAS. Like, Jainism says, Atma is, like, atomic, it should be in some part of the body. Some say that Atma is as good as the whole body. Some say it's beyond the body, okay? So, so these are the debates in different Indian philosophies, and there's no conclusive thing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, in my understanding, don't…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you shouldn't get into this black and white answer of which part of the body the mind exists. The human body… the human being is a wholesome composition of mind, atma, and the body. That's how, if you go, that would… that's our Rishi's understanding. That's… that's how our understandings have evolved.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How come strangers open up to a counselor? I have experience with persons who are close to me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's also need, it's also resonance, it's also the rapport you built in the first session, it's also how you lower down the defense mechanism. So it starts with the need. Person wants to vent out, wants to undergo the catharsis and therapy, it starts with need, but the other three are your skills, how you open up the person.
Dr. Karan Mittal: To a stranger who's sitting on the council's chair.
Dr. Karan Mittal: last week.
Vikram Chakilam: Those three, Prabhu. Are you going to, discuss those… the three other three?
Vikram Chakilam: Not for Gonslov.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Brookshi, I think the last question is for you. As per Brahma Samhita, 5 gross elements, mind, Buddhi, false Igo are layers of universe. Is our mind also part of higher layer of the universe?
GOVINDA Das: It depends upon where the mind is in the Gita.
GOVINDA Das: Banduratmat manastase naat may y'uatmana jita.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, Krishna in the sixth chapter explains that one who has elevated the mind, the very mind is the friend, that means friend means higher realm. Alright, so mind itself is not from the higher realm, the deity of the mind.
GOVINDA Das: in the… in the Bhagavatam, it talks, the deity of the mind is Lord Shiva.
GOVINDA Das: You know? And some places, Anirud also.
GOVINDA Das: The DT is on the higher realm, but my mind, where does it situate?
GOVINDA Das: Right? Yes, in the creation, in the beginning of the creation, the… the… The ego, the Hankara.
GOVINDA Das: Right? There is Tamu, there is sattva, and there is Rajo. So, mind comes from the sattvaguna, in the third camp of the Srimad Bhagavata.
GOVINDA Das: And Buddhi comes from Rajogodha, very interestingly.
GOVINDA Das: Even though Buddha is higher than the mind.
GOVINDA Das: But the creation of the mind comes from sattva, and Buddhi comes from Rajo.
GOVINDA Das: Why? Because mind has the power to also concentrate.
GOVINDA Das: One can stay in a peaceful place for a long time.
GOVINDA Das: But when we apply Buddhi, what does Buddhi do? Buddhi is part of a creative energy. So, creative energy cannot be
GOVINDA Das: made into…
GOVINDA Das: what do you call it, as you cannot make it frozen. Whenever Buddhi is there, it gives rise to creation. You're writing articles, you are speaking something, you're writing script, you are writing books.
GOVINDA Das: So, anything which creates is in Rajoguna, and Buddhi is the beginning of creation.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, yes, mind is of sattoguna.
GOVINDA Das: In regards to creation, but in regards to myself, your son, it depends upon where it is operating for you.
GOVINDA Das: Higher or lower?
GOVINDA Das: I think we'll stop here, no?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sergey Brooji has raised a hand, then we can start.
GOVINDA Das: and you still take one question, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oscar's…
Bhaskar G: I think it's Here's basketball.
GOVINDA Das: I can't hear you.
Bhaskar G: Hello, hello, can you hear me?
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
Bhaskar G: So, when we're talking about, thinking creates existence, you were also emphasizing about creating, the existence creates think… your thinking.
Bhaskar G: So, is it that there are two exclusive things, or both are true? Because, thinking creates existence also seems to be true, because our beliefs define our behavior.
Bhaskar G: And, so, so, are both the things true, or just one thing is true?
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, but because we were discussing the Western philosophy in regards to a particular philosopher who said that, thinking gives rise to existence, alright?
GOVINDA Das: Again, always… If you want to study Indian psychology.
GOVINDA Das: Never see from the perspective boxes.
GOVINDA Das: Always see from the perspective of integrated samagrata. Ompurdam.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: So when you see from Puranathwa, so what does it do? Existence gives rise to thinking, thinking gives rise to existence. So the pattern, thinking, feeling, willing, and action, they are continuous flow.
GOVINDA Das: Right. So, in our… in our, in our reality, they are integrated. One gives rise to other, other gives rise to previous one. It is called Paras, para…
GOVINDA Das: Our lambi. Paras, per our lambi. They're in… they're in, they're connected to each other.
GOVINDA Das: When you go back to the creation in the beginning of the Srishti, again, for the Bharatiyata, Srishti is not creation.
GOVINDA Das: The example sometime what Vigil got is like a watchmaker.
GOVINDA Das: Creation is not made. Creation is eternal, therefore we called it Sprakkariti.
GOVINDA Das: No… the part of the Prakriti, the manifested, like, when you study the scripture, when Brahmaji did Taposya.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Tapasya gave rise to creation. It was not thinking, it was not desire, because it is simply a manifest.
GOVINDA Das: So that is a big difference.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, when we study the Bible and Quran, it talks about creation.
GOVINDA Das: But when you study the Vedic scripture, we study Prakriti. The world of Prakriti and creation are totally different from each other.
GOVINDA Das: So therefore, yes.
GOVINDA Das: thinking gives rise to existence, existence gives rise to thinking, and therefore integrating both. Therefore, our existence, our thinking, our relationships, our spirituality are in harmony.
GOVINDA Das: then we grow in harmony. As much as we do not grow in harmony, that's much we experience Adharma within us.
GOVINDA Das: Does it make sense?
Bhaskar G: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, thank you.
GOVINDA Das: So it's the,
GOVINDA Das: Suraji, we can begin with you tomorrow morning, since, tomorrow evening, with our, display of the
GOVINDA Das: app.
GOVINDA Das: They're supposed to give their email ID you can share with them?
A-Suraj Racha: Yeah, so, one small addition.
A-Suraj Racha: So, we are having our Apple…
A-Suraj Racha: So… which will definitely present tomorrow in-house, and am I not audible?
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, Ben, Firsa, you are breaking.
A-Suraj Racha: Hello?
GOVINDA Das: Perselebreaking.
GOVINDA Das: That's breaking, we'll do it tomorrow.
A-Suraj Racha: Twitter?
GOVINDA Das: No, it was… it was breaking. You're on audio. Okay.
GOVINDA Das: Thank you for your kindness.
A-Suraj Racha: Residential.
GOVINDA Das: meet again tomorrow, 7.30. Our second session is basically seeing mind through the Faith-centric systems.
Lavina: Thank you.
Aarti Ganesh: National State High Chief.
Renuka Bhuta: That was true.
Sreenivas Gopal Das: Haley Krishna.
jithendra myla: Thank you, Brahuji. Very good.
jithendra myla: Yay.